This video is sponsored by Proton Mail.
>> From the dawn of time, humans have had
the urge to move between places and to
sometimes carry things with them. At
first, we relied on foot technology.
Then, we discovered the wheel and put
them under our boxes so they're easier
to drag along. We then invented horses
and put them in front of said boxes,
thus creating the coach. A word that
comes from the name of some random
Hungarian village called coach.
I'm not making this up. This is actually
the origin of the word. Just some random
Hungarian village where coaches used to
be made. It's called coach. It even has
a coach museum. Pretty cool. But as our
civilizations grew, the coach became
increasingly insufficient for inland
transportation. That is when the concept
of train travel was revealed to Robert
Stevenson in a Marmiteind induced fever
dream and the rest is history. On the
6th of October 1829, the village of
Rainhill in pre-rexit Britain was the
site of a competition that entered the
pages of history books. The Rainhill
trials, as they called it, was held to
determine whether locomotives really
were the future of rail transport. Back
in those days, the world's first
commercial railway line was about to
start operation between Manchester and
Liverpool, and company leadership wasn't
sure exactly how it should operate. They
did not want horses. So, the logical
solution they ended up with was to have
giant steam engines next to the tracks,
which would drag carriages with cables.
But George Stevenson begged to differ.
He saw through management stackro
attitude and proposed to put the steam
engines on the rails instead. What if
instead of all these cables, the steam
engines would drag the cars directly and
move along with them? Company management
agreed to test the idea in a great
competition of experimental steam
locomotives with a fabulous grand prize
of £55,000 in today's money. Of the five
locomotives, one of them being just a
horse on a treadmill. Only Stevenson's
rocket could finish the circuit, winning
the grand prize and convincing
management that steam locomotives were
indeed the way to go. Thus began the age
of steam locomotion, which is where many
politicians remain mentally to this day.
A notable side effect of the Rain Hill
trials is that many people consider
Stevenson to be the inventor of
locomotives and Rocket to be the first
one ever built. This is not true. Plenty
of locomotives got built before and
Rocket wasn't even Stevenson's first.
The first locomotive ever built was
probably Trevik's thing in 1804. I'm
saying probably because the concept
itself is actually pretty simple. Since
before Christ, we've had steam engines
that did stuff. From the 16th century,
we've had steam engines that did useful
stuff. And from 1764, ones that actually
functioned well. Put such a steam engine
in a coach and you got a steam car.
Steam, steam, steam. Got to step on the
steam. Put the steam car on tracks and
there you go. Trevik was the first one
to do it on record, but who knows? Maybe
someone else did it somewhere else.
maybe as a miniature or something like
that small model steam train Americans
sent to Japan as a gift in 1854 in
exchange for opening up the country for
trade which they had set up in a garden
and a bunch of highranking officials sat
around it or on it watching the model
train go round and around. One year
later the shogunit ceremonially opened
the Tokyo Naguya Shinkansenk. So trains
great. We have the locomotive we have
the cars. We have the tracks. Let's
start connecting places. Hell yeah. But
oh no, what's that? Something is in the
way. Something called geography.
Valleys, mountains, hills, rivers. How
do you get through them? Well, usually
you don't. Boring some special cases
because speed contrary to techro ideas
is not always the most important factor
in rail transit. For example, if a rail
line is mostly used to haul, say iron
ore, speed doesn't really matter. Or
doesn't spoil and the people at the end
of the track only care about a steady
continuous shipment of it. This is why
things like the Hyperport are complete
non-starters. That's when some tech pros
wanted to ram an elevated cargo
hyperloop through Europe so the goods
that spent 2 weeks at sea to get there
can continue on really fast. Why? If I'm
in Europe selling those stupid [__]
toys where they call the Furbies, but
it's Tik Tok brain rot. Laboo, right? It
even sounds like something a brain
damaged teenager would come up with.
Laboo. Laboo. Where am I? Laboo. I want
Laboo. So, if I'm in Europe selling
those, cashing in on the algorithm
induced consumerrist hysteria, I don't
care how fast the labu gets to me. All I
care about is that I get my box of labu
each week so I can sell them at a 700%
markup. Similarly, the first rail lines
didn't necessarily need to be fast. They
needed to be reliable and consistent.
So, lines tended to follow natural
formations. If there was a river going
through a mountainous region, the rail
would follow the river, for example.
Today, though, our requirements for rail
are different. Passenger rail has become
so important that it's no longer enough
to just get to places. You want to do it
as fast as possible for rail to be
viable because trains have competition.
Cars and highways and oh no, what's that
thing driving towards us? Crap. It's the
new cancel culture ready to fire us like
Jimmy Kimmel if we say something that
triggers them. Time to keep your private
correspondents safe from the mega social
justice warriors. And today's sponsor,
Proton Mail, is here to do exactly that.
Proton Mail is a privacy focused
end-to-end encrypted email service made
to keep your personal data safe from
unauthorized eyes. If you accidentally
write something the woke mega mob finds
unacceptable, well, now they can't read
it anymore thanks to Proton Mail's
encryption system available for both
personal and business use. Proton Mail
is a free service with optional paid
plans for additional benefits. Switching
to Proton Mail is easy, even if you
already have an email address at one of
the big providers. All thanks to the
easy switch feature that lets you set up
email forwarding with just a few clicks.
And you can also import your calendar
and contacts. Go to proton.me/adam
something to get started with Proton
Mail for free with optional paid plans
for additional benefits and features.
That's proton.me/adam
something. Thank you for checking out
Proton Mail. So if you build a highway
next to an old rail line, dear Czech
government, and you do not upgrade the
rail line, dear Czech rail
administration, then everyone will take
the [__] highway with their giant
SUVs on their way to their jobs in
Prague. And then more people on bicycles
will die in heavy traffic on the
dangerous dog [__] bike infrastructure.
Dear Dyak, okay, to be fair, the Czech
government is also aware of the need to
upgrade railways, not bike paths. Shoda
doesn't allow them. And there have been
some very good projects already. For
example, the line between Prague and
Cheske or Budwise, that's where the beer
is from. It was upgraded, realigned, and
its stop speed increased to 200 km/h.
I'm sorry, up to 200 km/h, which is rail
director at Newspeak for a 160 km/h
track where trains with a tilt box can
sometimes do 200 km/h when the weather
is nice and the planets align. Still,
it's a good project and they are
continuing it. This has led to trains on
the line becoming competitive with the
car. From Prague to Budweis, it takes
about an hour and 40 minutes of driving.
same as the train. And there are some
other projects like the new high-speed
tunnel between Prague and Brisden,
another tunnel between Prague and Bilzen
towards Bavaria, the Bruno Predto
realignment, and plans for a bunch of
straight express lines where
long-distance traffic will be
transferred to from the squiggly local
lines. Austrians went even bigger. The
Coron tunnel, which is about to be
inaugurated this year, is a colossal
undertaking. A brand new 130 km long
line with a 100 plus bridges, 50 km of
tunnels, and 23 new stations. cutting
down travel times from 3 hours to just
45 minutes. Absolutely insane. These
massive expensive projects are necessary
to bring the level of railways to 21st
century standards because no country
starts out with a near-perfect rail
network and geography. Or do they? What
if you had a country that started with
excellent geography and a wellplanned
rail network already in the 19th
century? One that would basically
correspond to 21st century geometric
standards. And what if that country,
despite this incredible one-of-a-kind
legendary starting position, [__] it
all up beyond belief? Well, Austria has
a neighbor. No, no, no. To the east. A
country called Hungary.
When it comes to rail, Hungary has
everything. A landscape flattered than a
frying pan, no mountains, barely any
hills even, and a rail network that was
actually very well built from the
beginning, meaning the 19th century.
Lines were built mostly straight. They
were integrated into cities, had decent
capacity. Later upgrades in the early
20th century saw the double tracking of
most main lines and further
straightenings. Under Soviet occupation,
upgrades continued, and by the 1980s,
the Hungarian rail network was a thing
to behold. It wasn't perfect, and
Hungary was still a poor country, but
still it was quite good. Budapest had
not one but three major railway
stations. The southern station in the
west, the eastern station in the middle,
and the western station in the north.
Rolling stock was rather modern for the
time which later included domestically
produced push pull trains that sort of
look like modern electric multiple units
from a distance. Decent tracks, great
geometry, good rolling stock, consistent
service, a robust domestic production,
pushpull suburban operations with
widespread use of control cars just like
in distant famed Germany with their
brand new domestically made suburban
push pulls with even an intercity
variant which was very close to the
operational concept of today's rail
jets. the flagship [__] service of
Austrian railways and increasingly the
Czech railways. Hungarian railways had
these two decades before its time. But
then came the 1990s, the dark age of
rail, except in Japan. Damn, the
shogunit was really right on the money.
Welcome to the '90s. The Soviet Union is
gone. The world is opening up rapidly.
Western capitalism reigns supreme upon
the ruins of Soviet state capitalism.
Giant bland glass and steel towers are
all the rage. personal computers,
Japanese gadgets, cars that actually
turned on in the morning, suburbs,
highways, blue jeans, the LA riots. The
old was out and the modern was in, which
in Hungary meant that the geriatric
oligarchic mafia leading the country
until then could finally stop pretending
that they gave a [__] about any leftist
ideals and immediately transitioned into
today's right-wing conservative boomers.
and right-wing conservative boomers love
cars, airplanes, and highways. While
being anywhere between neutral to openly
hostile towards public transit,
including rail, this meant that each
time the state needed more money, rail
was always the first on the chopping
block. Hungarian railways, a robust and
solid system, would thus begin its long
decline. State investment dried up. The
country's once massive rail industrial
base went bankrupt. Rolling stock
procurement ground to a halt. Train
stations were literally left to rot.
Services like catering were gradually
abandoned. The once elegant head
stations were flooded with trashy cheap
shops and pubs growing like tumors on
the buildings. This is the southern
station or daily. It's a very high
quality modernist building that looks
really cool. Well, it did before it was
littered by cheap stores and pubs. Its
airy transparent glass lower floor was
plastered up with gody advertisements.
And they also let a [__] plastic tent
be put there, serving as the outdoor
terrace for a cheap pub for local
alcoholics. The white marble facade
started falling down and had to be taken
off. Now a massive net covers the entire
front, permanently darkening the
elegant, spacious ticket hall, which is
now in shambles. The ceiling is ripped
off. The large exits leading to the
street are fenced off permanently. Half
of the main hall used to be a food court
type of thing. Now it's all closed down
and abandoned. And if we look at what's
on the tracks, the situation is even
worse. The rolling stock base is at its
very limit. Still running passenger cars
built in the early60s. Except for one
procurement of Euro city cars in the
1990s and of toddler suburban EMUs
bought using EU money. They did
absolutely nothing. Oh wait, that's not
true. Enter the Intercity Plus.
Hungary's brand new domestic car renewal
program.
A project that failed so hilariously it
was killed before even reaching the
halfway point. Those newly built cars,
of which there are a grand total of 92,
often run on the infamous Hungaria Euro
city between Budapest and Berlin.
Infamous because those cars are such
colossal pieces of [__] It's a miracle
they reach their destination. Nothing
works on these things. The AC, the
reservation system, the onboard
information systems, the Wi-Fi, the
power plugs, the intercom, something is
always broken.
Also, I hope you like it when the chair
you're sitting on has a sharp jotting
part right under your shoulder blade
when it presses and cuts into your skin
for hours because that is the exact kind
of seat on those trains. I've been
listening to Czech train people's
complaints about these cars for years.
Even back then when Czech railways
itself wasn't running the best rolling
stock there either, mostly BMZ cars from
Simmering, but at least those [__]
worked. And now they have decided to
upgrade their game further with the
deployment of brand new railjet trains.
permanently coupled push pulls which now
completely covered the Prague Berlin
route with a single Hungaria left in the
schedule like a pig at a beauty contest.
But what's this? Oh my god, it can't be.
Has the Hungarian government heard the
calling of modern times? Wow, they want
to order the same trains as the checks,
thereby revitalizing their entire
international network, which would allow
their current cars to be shifted down to
domestic routes, and we could finally
get rid of all the old obsolete junk.
Wo! or renovation plans for the western
station Yugati. This looks great. It
seems like the long decline of Hungarian
rail is over. Oh, wait, never mind. They
asked all those projects due to a lack
of funds because the EU wouldn't give
them money because they stole too much.
But don't worry, plebs. In the meantime,
the ruling government's elite gets to
sail around on their yachts. And Orban
has built a personal castle for himself
next to his village football stadium
that has more seats than the village has
inhabitants. Oh, what's that? The rail
system is falling apart. Fine, fine,
fine. We will widen the M1 highway to
six lanes. Yep. Hey everybody, future
Adam here. Jumping in real quick.
Shortly after this video was completed,
there was a major derailment on one of
the Hungarian branch lines. Luckily, no
dead, just two injured. And the reason
for this derailment was the catastrophic
state of the tracks. And as of now, we
have confirmation from railway circles
that the rescue utility train that was
sent to the location derailed as well,
which is needless to say absolutely
incredible.
As of now, the Minister of
Transportation has already commented on
the issue, promising line closures
because of this accident. I legitimately
don't know what to say at this point.
Anyway, back to the video. But wait,
they did reconstruct the Budapest Vienna
line parallel to the M1 highway. Well,
about one sixth of it after it has been
left to rot for 30 years. Seriously, the
rail jet that travels 230 km/h around
Vienna was forced to go 80 to 60 km/h on
multiple Hungarian sections because of
bad track alignment they never fixed or
for fear that the kenary poles would
[__] collapse for three decades. But
finally, this line was reconstructed and
it happened like lightning. One day, we
saw news about the wooden screws having
rotted out or something. So now the
tracks were in critical condition. So
boom, here we go. Reconstruction. Get
ready for a full lockout. It happened so
fast the government didn't even notify
other rail carriers on time in breach of
agreements and contracts they've signed.
But usually such reconstructions take
years of preparation. So where did they
get all these workers and equipment
overnight? Well, it turns out this whole
project was a type of scam. Basically,
the tracks were in bad shape, but
nowhere near critical. The real problem
was on the Budapest Belgrade line, a
partially new, partially reconstructed
line between the two capitals with a
planned top speed of 160 km/h. There
were some problems if you can believe
it. First, the cost, about€ 10 million
per kilometer on completely flat terrain
with no obstacles. Highspeed rail
usually starts from 12 million and
that's built for 250 km per hour or
more. Also, the Hungarian government
financed it from a massive Chinese loan,
the details of which they classified for
the next 10 years. And yet, this line is
a Chinese geopolitical project. It's
meant to connect Europe with the Chinese
port in Tessaloniki. So, then why is
Hungary taking a Chinese loan to build
this project for the benefit of China?
This is the geopolitical equivalent of
Cockoldry. Oh, but it will return the
investment. Yeah, estimates put it
between 979 and 2,400
years. But there was another [__]
problem. The tracks need this thing
called train control so you always know
what's where and you don't crash trains
into each other. They wanted to install
ETCS or European train control system or
ERTMS if you really insist. They gave
the job to the Chinese who also use ETCs
for their own rail network. They can't
do it because their rail system is
highly standardized and simplified.
European lines famously aren't. So now
there are rumors that they will instead
install a Hungarian legacy control
system called Domino developed in 1955
which only allows for a top speed of 120
km/h and will increase the price tag by
further eurom millions. The line itself
was built by Orban's friend group like
typical Balkans mafia [__] But with the
Chinese [__] up the train control the
whole project had to stop. No works, no
money, and the letter is completely
unacceptable for Orban's friends. So
they quickly made up a story about the
catastrophic defects on the Budapest
Vienna line which needed to be fixed
immediately or else. And then they
transferred all their workers and
equipment from the Budapest Belgrade
line to the Budapest Vienna line. And
even then all they did was compensate
for the lack of proper cyclical
maintenance. And now the line is just
sitting there again slowly decaying
waiting for the next big overhaul in
three decades because Hungarian railways
doesn't get enough funding even for
essential maintenance. Train control
failure, traction line failure,
locomotive breakdown, missing cars,
derailment, a complete collapse of the
mainline to Hungary's main resort area
during the summer holiday peak. Take
your pick. But to show how on top of
things the government is following the
massive summer holiday mainline
collapse, the transportation minister
ordered 300 buses to Budapest from all
over the country to stand ready in case
there is another breakdown. So, we had
300 buses and their drivers simply
milling around the station all day doing
nothing aside from clogging up the
streets because the collapse happened
the day before, not on that day. Also,
they failed to provide toilets or even
shade to those drivers. Still, the facts
are clear. The Hungarian state cannot
even organize traffic on one [__]
line anymore without constant breakdowns
or run one [__] train with a
consistent level of service. Like, look
at this. This is a crossber intercity
train between Mishko and Koshita. What
is this [__] a 6-axxle V63 locomotive
intended for heavy freight trains, a
repainted second generation icy car from
the 70s, a suburban car meant for the
railways pushpull trains, and a
secondhand ex-ustrian Yenbacher car also
meant for suburban service. Followed by
three Slovakian intercity cars, all the
same type and the same level of service.
Or how about this? I had to check in
with the source for this one. That car
right there is a Mav Rail Tours standard
class Shiran car which they got a
secondhand from Switzerland which is
normally part of special occasion trains
or experience rides. Such a car is seen
here as part of a regular long-distance
train because they had nothing else. And
oh hey, what's this car on the right on
this intercity category train?
It's a secondhand Yenbacher suburban
car. And the reason for the Hungarian
Railways Franken trains is that they
really have nothing else. They're not
messing with you on purpose. What you
see is what they got. This is all they
can scrunch up from the depot in the
morning and the little they got left is
getting less and less every single day.
Meanwhile, delays have gotten so common
that the railways were ordered to stop
publishing delay statistics and to hide
the trains with greater delays from the
information system. Later on, they just
killed the entire system altogether and
they only restored it somewhat after
widespread public outrage and ridicule.
Now delay statistics are all bundled
together with suburban rail which is
very high frequency and operates mostly
with Swissade EMUs bought with EU cache
on the scanned fuel lines renovated also
with EU cache. So those are mostly
punctual thanks to the EU. That way when
combining suburban and longd distance
the overall punctuality is 80%. But we
know for a fact that right before they
stopped publishing detailed statistics
in August 2024 the punctuality of
longdistance trains was just 32.8%.
And this is when we ignore delays of up
to 5 minutes. Things have only gotten
worse since then. Oh, and Hungarian
railways recently also got caught
dumping waste illegally. Here we have a
van with the Hungarian state railways
logo pulling up to a trash heap below
and underpass and dumping some used
furniture. Great. As a result of a
right-wing conservative boomer oligarchy
leading the country, Hungarian rail has
become a joke and in my opinion the
worst in Europe. Yes, yes, yes, there
are worse systems in absolute terms, but
those usually never had any promise to
begin with. You can show me pictures of
Bulgarian main lines or something where
the track is a bunch of branches thrown
in the mud with two steel pipes slept on
top. But like, yeah, no [__] It's the
Balkans. It's always been like that.
Hungary, on the other hand, had promise.
They had and still have everything for a
worldclass rail system only requiring a
relatively small investment. No need to
dig colossal tunnel systems. The tracks
are already there and are completely
straight. And yet they refuse to fund
even the bare minimum maintenance of
what little they have left. Austria,
Czecha, Poland, Germany, Switzerland,
Italy, pretty much all other countries
in the region are shoveling money into
rail as Hungary does nothing but slowly
rots away as Victor Orban flies around
the world on private jets and the
country's leadership drinks champagne
aboard their yachts on the Adriatic Sea.
Hopefully though, not for long.
Sir, would you like some champagne?
Goodby inch.
[Music]